C. W. Kahles Papers
C. W. Kahles Papers
1886-1976
1900-1930
Kahles, C. W. (Charles William)
2 linear ft.
Biographical information, correspondence, photos, personal memorabilia, clippings, published material, 1 original oil painting, original cartoons and photocopies of cartoons, including representative material from Hairbreadth Harry and examples of Kahles' numerous other strips.
2670150
Biographical History
Charles William Kahles (1878-1931), commonly known as C. W. Kahles, was an American cartoonist and creator of the newspaper comic strip Hairbreadth Harry.
Kahles was born in Lengfurt, Bavaria, Germany on January 12, 1878. When Kahles was six, his family moved to the United States, settling in the Windsor Terrace section of Brooklyn. As a child, Kahles sketched the natural environment around him. He and his brother worked as apprentices in a stained glass shop and Kahles went on to study at the Pratt Institute and the Brooklyn Art School.
In the 1890s, Kahles worked as a news artist for the New York Recorder, then Grit based in Williamsport, Pennsylvania before returning to New York to work for the New York World. In the early 1900s Kahles embarked on his career as a very prolific cartoonist. His Clarence the Cop ran in the New York World from 1900-1909 while Kahles began Sandy Highflyer, Airship Man in May of 1902. Juggling these strips and others for several years, Kahles also contributed to magazines such as Judge where his The Yarns of Captain Fibb appeared. Kahles drew in several different styles and utilized caricature, satire, realism, suspense and fantasy.
In 1906, Hairbreadth Harry debuted with the Philadelphia Press and continued until the paper left the syndication business in 1915. McClure Syndicate brought Hairbreadth Harry back a few months later in January 1916. In 1923 the comic strip was moved to the Ledger Syndicate and from 1926-1928 several two reel silent Hairbreadth Harry movies were produced. After Kahles death, F.O. Alexander continued Hairbreadth Harry until 1939.
It has been noted by his family and authors that Kahles often worked too much. As a hobby and for relaxation, he pursued painting and also enjoyed traveling in his touring car. Still his career adversely affected his health. Kahles suffered from inflammatory rheumatism at a young age and developed heart problems. C.W. Kahles died January 21, 1931 in Great Neck, Long Island, New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The C. W. Kahles Papers provide representative examples of Kahles’ prolific career. The papers include biographical information, correspondence, photographs, clippings, examples of Kahles' magazine illustrations, 1 original oil painting, original cartoons and photocopies of cartoons, and material from Hairbreadth Harry as well as Kahles' other strips.
Arrangement of the Collection
The C. W. Kahles Papers are organized into several small series. Please consult the detailed inventory below for more information.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
A limited edition, numbered copy of The Pleiades Club Yearbook from 1913 which includes a drawing by Kahles has been removed from this collection and sent to Rare Books.
Subject and Genre Headings
Kahles, C. W. (Charles William); Hairbreadth Harry.; The Kelly Kids (comic strip); Clarence the Cop (comic strip); The Perils of Submarine Boating (comic strip); Sandy Highflyer the Airship Man (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Adirondack Mountains (N.Y.); Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Biography files.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. C. H. Straut, 1968-1970, 1977.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Pleiades Club, 1907-1908; 1913 (Oversize 1)
  - Royalty statements, 1933; 1935 (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous biographical information, 1913; 1968; 1976; includes a clipping about Kahles' divorce, a list of his comic strips and a speech given by his daughter (Oversize 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence- fan mail, 1930 (Oversize 1)
  - Incoming correspondence- postcards, 1912; 1915; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence- Joseph Hausleiter, 1895; Kahles apprenticed in Hausleiter's stained glass shop. (Oversize 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence- Estelle P. Kahles, 1916 (Oversize 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence- Jessie Kahles, 1922-1923; 1928-1930; undated (Oversize 1)
- Photographs
  - Adirondacks, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Personal and family photographs, 1886-1930 (Oversize 1)
- Clippings
  - Potsy (comic strip), 1967 (Oversize 1)
  - Hairbreadth Harry, 1924; 1926 (Oversize 1)
- Magazine illustrations
  - Various examples of Kahles' work from Life, Judge and other publications, 1909; 1912; 1914; 1917; primarily tearsheets, proofs and photocopies. Included is The Yarns of Captain Fibb and a copy of an illustration that appeared in Life in 1918, the original of which was given to Herbert Hoover. (Oversize 1)
- Hairbreadth Harry
  - Photographs, circa 1926-1928; stills from several Hairbreadth Harry films (Oversize 1)
  - Samples, 1923; 1930-1931 (Oversize 1)
  - Comic strips, 1906-1907; 1916; 1930; undated; primarily tearsheets and photocopies (Oversize 1)
- Comic strips
  - Examples Kahles' work, 1900; 1902; circa 1900-1909; undated; primarily tearsheets and photocopies of other comic strips drawn by Kahles including The Kelly Kids, Clarence the Cop, The Perils of Submarine Boating and Sandy Highflyer, the Airship Man. (Oversize 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Original painting of the Adirondacks by Kahles, circa 1904-1905 (Oversize 1)
  - National Cartoonists Society drawing, 1963; photocopy of a drawing dedicated to Kahles' daughter Jessie, featuring work by several NCS cartoonists. (Oversize 1)